Guide to the Nelson Sullivan Video Collection 1976 - 1989 MSS.357
Fales Library and Special Collections
Nelson Sullivan Video Collection
1976 - 1989
Fales Library and Special Collections
Sullivan, Nelson
MSS.357
12 Linear Feet
Nelson Sullivan (1948-1989) was a video artist who documented downtown New York City in the 1980s. The Nelson Sullivan Video Collection contains videorecordings, film, photographic material, and objects relating to the city's art world and LGBT community as well as performances in clubs, house parties, and interactions with Sullivan's friends from 1976-1989.
Arrangement
The archivist preserved the original order of the video collection as donated by the estate of Nelson Sullivan. The series of videorecordings have not been chronologically or thematically rearranged.
Biographical/Historical Note
Nelson Sullivan (1948-1989) was a video artist who documented downtown New York City in the 1980s. Originally from South Carolina, Sullivan moved to Manhattan in the 1970s and began filming the city's art world and gay scene. He captured John Sex, Sylvia Miles, RuPaul, and other performers at downtown bars and nightclubs including Danceteria, the Limelight, Palladium, and the Pyramid Club. Sullivan also chronicled house parties at his apartment at 5 Ninth Avenue in the Meatpacking District, gallery openings, park and street festivals, conversations with taxi drivers, and the ruminations of his friends including fashion designer Alexis Del Lago and journalist Michael Musto on film. He recorded almost 2,000 hours of tape, at first using a VHS-loading camera and later an 8mm video camera. Sullivan's filmmaking is recognizable for its point of view transitions and its stream-of-consciousness narration. He also often pointed a wide-angle lens at his own face while filming to record his commentary on the people, performances, or events that he captured. Sullivan made films up until his death from a heart attack on July 4, 1989.
Sources:
A Very Short Introduction to Nelson Sullivan
The 5 Ninth Avenue Project
John Sanchez Interview with Dick Richards about xlNelson Sullivan
Scope and Content
The Nelson Sullivan Video Collection is a collection of videorecordings made by video artist Nelson Sullivan (1948-1989). The collection consists of videotapes, film, photographic material and objects related to the city's art world and LGBT community as well as performances in clubs, house parties, and interactions with Sullivan's friends. The videos cover the period 1976-1989.
The collection is comprised of four series:
Series I: Videorecordings contains 8 boxes of videorecordings made by Nelson Sullivan.
Series II: Film (currently unavailable)
Series III: Photographic Material contains 1 binder of slides covering the period between 1975 and 1977.
Series IV: Objects (currently unavailable)
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Provenance
The Nelson Sullivan Video Collection was donated to Fales Library by the estate of Nelson Sullivan, overseen by Dick Richards, David Goldman, and Robert Coddington operating collectively as the 5 Ninth Avenue Project, in September 2012.
Related Material at Fales Library and Special Collections
April Palmieri Papers
Downtown Flyers and Invitations
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Access copies for some materials are available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Please contact fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Other Finding Aids
Content notes are available in an external document. Created by New York University's Media Preservation Unit, the notes describe the content of the recordings as observed by a technician during digitization. These notes include: description of the action, recognizable names and locations, and screen captures. For access to this document, please contact the audiovisual archivist at Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu.
Performance art -- New York (State) -- New York.; Queer theory.; Gays in popular culture.; Gays -- Political activity -- New York (State) -- New York.; Gay men -- United States.; DVDs.; Self-portraits; Videocassettes.; Videocassettes.; Video recordings -- Social aspects.; 8mm.; Downtown Collection.; Charles, RuPaul, 1960-; Nevelson, Louise, 1899-1988; Sex, John; Miles, Sylvia, 1932-; Gunn, Moses, 1929-1993; Rotello, Gabriel; Warhol, Andy, 1928-1987; Haring, Keith; Musto, Michael, 1955-; Woodlawn, Holly; Field, Patricia, 1941-; Arias, Joey, 1955-; Eichelberger, Ethyl, 1945-1990; Lady Bunny
- Series I: Video recordings, 1976 - 1988; 243787
  Arrangement
  This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
  - Ameri/cain Gothic by Paul Carter Harrison, undated; ID: 357.0001; 243788 (Box 1, Media ID: 357.0001, Case 357.0001)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Currently available.
    Scope and Content
    This video shows an undated performance of Paul Carter Harrison's play Ameri/cain Gothic, starring Sylvia Miles and Moses Gunn and directed by Woodie King, Jr.
    Existence and Location of Copies
    DVD access copy available.
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Original format: VHS
  - Now Explosion at the Pyramid Club, November 16, 1983; ID: 357.0002; 244864 (Box 1, Media ID: 357.0002, Case 357.0002_pt.1, Case 357.0002_pt.2)
    DVD access copy available. Please request Part 1 and Part 2.
    Original Format: VHS
    Part one of this video from November 16, 1983, shows Nelson spending time in the Pyramid Club dressing room prior to a performance by the Atlanta, Georgia, band The Now Explosion. Among those in the video are Deloris French, John Sex, and members of The Now Explosion.
    Part two of this video is a continuation of The Now Explosion performing at the Pyramid Club. After their performance, there is a dance contest with Doctor Tony and Joan Ransom from the PTA, then footage from the Pyramid Club dressing room after the show. Finally, there is footage of a party Nelson attends in "Bobby and John's" apartment.
  - Chelsea Hotel (tape #1), November 20, 1983; ID: 357.0012; 243828 (Box 1, Media ID: 357.0012, Case 357.0012_pt.1, Case 357.0012_pt.2)
    Original Tape 1 (of 2)
    The first disc of this video starts with footage from the morning of November 20, 1983, when the Chelsea Hotel lobby is being prepared for a party. Nelson goes to room 604 to spend time with friends, including Sandy Dancer, Michael Musto, and Deloris French. Sandy Dancer prepares for her performance later in the day. When a news camera crew interviews Sandy, she says that the party is a birthday celebration for the Chelsea.
    The second disc begins with people flowing in and out of room 604 while Sandy Dancer finishes preparing for her performance. There is a dance performance in the stairwell before the main party in the lobby, where, among others, Sandy Dancer and Michael Musto perform. Ed Koch appears after a couple songs in order to honor the Chelsea Hotel on its 100th anniversary and declare November 20, 1983 Chelsea Hotel Day. Koch also presents playwright Arthur Miller with a plaque honoring his time living at the Chelsea. Miller gives brief remarks before the unveiling of his plaque. Ulick O'Connor speaks on behalf of the history of the Chelsea, and there are a couple more performances.
  - Chelsea Hotel (tape #2), November 20, 1983; ID: 357.0003; 243818 (Box 1, Media ID: 357.0003, Case 357.0003)
    DVD access available.
    Original Tape 2 (of 2)
    This video documents performances and a party in the Chelsea Hotel lobby on November 20, 1983. Towards the end of the night, someone in the hotel accidentally pulls a fire alarm and everyone moves outside temporarily. Among those featured are Sandy Dancer, Sylvia Miles, and Cookie Mueller.
    Current DVD is damaged and skips from around 56 minutes to 58 minutes.
  - Joshua at Darinka, June 13, 1986; ID: 357.0004; 243819 (Box 1, Media ID: 357.0004, Case 357.0004)
    On June 13, 1986, Nelson films a performance by Joshua at Darinka. The Because Family Picnic (John, Dina, and Joshua) performs in between two sets by Joshua. For a short amount of time, Nelson goes backstage and speaks with the performers. The video ends with Nelson walking alone down the street.
  - White Trash Night at Pizza-a-Go-Go, October 10, 1984; ID: 357.0005; 243820 (Box 1, Media ID: 357.0005, Case 357.0005)
    The video starts with Nelson and friends driving to Pizza-a-Go-Go for White Trash Night on October 10, 1984. When they arrive, Nelson wanders around the building before Michael Musto and the Must's performance starts. He bumps into Musto in the dressing room getting ready and warming up. Then, Michael Musto and the Must perform covers of popular songs by girl groups. After the show, Nelson goes backstage with the musicians and others for a while before going to the kitchen, where a Beatles cover band is performing. Then, Nelson and friends drive around and end up in a cafe.
  - Hollywood Hell #1, December 3, 1983; ID: 357.0013; 243829 (Box 1, Media ID: 357.0013, Case 357.0013)
    Video of the first part of the December 3, 1983 performance of Hollywood Hell, a comedy by Michael Musto starring Crystal Field and directed by John Albano at Theater for a New City.
  - Hollywood Hell #2, December 3, 1983; ID: 357.0006; 243821 (Box 1, Media ID: 357.0006, Case 357.0006)
    Video of the second part of the December 3, 1983 performance of Hollywood Hell, a comedy by Michael Musto starring Crystal Field and directed by John Albano at Theater for a New City.
  - Tabboo! and Shazork at Limelight, April 1, 1986; ID: 357.0007; 243823 (Box 1, Media ID: 357.0007, Case 357.0007)
    Access DVD available by appointment only.
    Nelson and his friends get dinner near the Chelsea Hotel before heading to Limelight for a show on April 1, 1986. When they arrive at Limelight, Nelson records the performers getting ready to perform in the dressing room. Then he moves to the dancefloor to record the audience before Tabboo!'s puppet show. After that ends, Shazork (Lady Bunny, DJ Dmitri Brill, and Sister Dimension's band) takes the stage. After the show, Nelson heads back stage briefly before leaving Limelight and heading to the a restaurant, where the video ends.
  - Atlanta: RuPaul at Weekends and Larry Tee's Celebrity Club, February 1986; ID: 357.0008; 243824 (Box 1, Media ID: 357.0008, Case 357.0008)
    The video starts with RuPaul gogo dancing at the Atlanta nightclub Weekends on February 27, 1986, then Nelson goes into RuPaul's private dressing room with Larry Tee and a couple of others. When RuPaul finishes his set, he joins the group. The video jumps to the next day, with Nelson spending time in a friend's house. His friend then gives him a tour on a drive through Atlanta on their way to lunch at Burton's Grill. The tour continues before they return to the house where Larry Tee and others have gathered to watch some recorded performances. Larry Tee then takes Nelson on a drive to what will become Larry Tee's Celebrity Club for a tour, which is still under construction. The video jumps again, to Nelson chatting with drag queens (Sultra, Wanda, and others) getting ready for the night and then doing a private performance/interview for Nelson. Finally, the video jumps to recordings of music videos by Spencer Thorton for The Now Explosion, RuPaul, and an unknown band. The video cuts off at the beginning of a clip titled "RuPaul, Tune-Up King."
  - Atlanta #1, August 16, 1983; ID: 357.0149; 244465 (Box 5, Media ID: 357.0149, Case 357.0149)
  - Atlanta (2): David Goldman's Party and Butthole Surfers at 688, February 28, 1986; ID: 357.0014; 243830 (Box 1, Media ID: 357.0014, Case 357.0014_pt.1, Case 357.0014_pt.2)
    In disc one, Nelson is in Atlanta at a house party at David Goldman's with Lahoma, Lurleen, and James at the beginning of this video dated February 28, 1986. The video then jumps to a Butthole Surfers concert at 688 later that night.
    Disc two is a continuation of the Butthole Surfers footage. Nelson leaves 688 with friends, and the last eleven minutes contain no footage.
  - Atlanta #3, August 1983; ID: 357.0161; 244488 (Box 6, Media ID: 357.0161, Case 357.0161)
  - Atlanta #4, August 1983; ID: 357.0162; 244489 (Box 6, Media ID: 357.0162, Case 357.0162)
  - RuPaul at Danceteria, October 12, 1984; ID: 357.0009; 243825 (Box 1, Media ID: 357.0009, Case 357.0009)
    Currently Available.
    On October 12, 1984, Nelson attended RuPaul's performance in Danceteria. The video starts with a group getting ready in RuPaul's dressing room, then shows all of the performance, featuring special guest Miss Felicia. After the show, Nelson goes backstage to congratulate RuPaul and Felicia on the show, and he spends the rest of the recording the group hanging out there.
  - Louise Nevelson in Conversation at the Guggenheim, March 5, 1986; ID: 357.0010; 243826 (Box 1, Media ID: 357.0010, Case 357.0010)
    Nelson and Sylvia Miles attend a dialogue between sculptor Louise Nevelson and critic and editor of New Criterion Hilton Kramer at the Guggenheim in this video, dated March 5, 1986. The conversation is in celebration of Nevelson's being awarded The Great Artist Series Award by New York University's Gallatin Division, for her contribution to international art and culture. After the talk, Nelson and Sylvia go to the reception in the Guggenheim's rotunda, where they speak with Louise.
  - Casanova by Ethyl Eichelberger, March 15, 1986; ID: 357.0011; 243827 (Box 1, Media ID: 357.0011, Case 357.0011)
    Nelson records performers getting ready for the March 15, 1986 show of Ethyl Eichelberger's campy comedy Casanova at the Performing Garage, starring Eichelberger, Lady Bunny, Lola Pashalinski, Katy Dierlam, and Barbara Wise. Nelson briefly goes backstage after the performance, where among the crowds, Sylvia Miles and Peter Hujar are present.
  - Hapi Phace at Pompeii Gallery and Bye Bye Birdie at The Saint, March 27, 1986; ID: 357.0015; 243831 (Box 1, Media ID: 357.0015, Case 357.0015)
    DVD acces copy available.
    This March 27, 1986 video shows Hapi Phace giving Nelson a tour of his show at Pompeii Gallery. Nelson then attends the midnight performance of Scott Wittman's production of Bye Bye Birdie, presented by Gabriel Rottello at The Saint.
  - Nelson's Birthday, March 15, 1986; ID: 357.0016; 243832 (Box 1, Media ID: 357.0016, Case 357.0016_pt.1, Case 357.0016_pt.2)
    Disc one of this video starts with Nelson receiving a phone call from Liz to make plans on March 15, 1986. Then Nelson spends time with his dog, Blackout, and his cats, Freddie and Eddie, telling them that it's his birthday. He takes Blackout for a short walk before heading to 7A Cafe to meet his friends, including Michael Musto. Nelson, Michael, and Liz then travel to Musto's family home.
    In disc two, Nelson, Michael, and Liz finally arrive at the Musto's family home in Bensonhurst and chat with Michael's family. They then drive to Albert's new house, receive a tour, and eat dinner. Nelson, Michael, and Liz leave Albert's apartment, and the video ends with them in the car.
  - Shazork at Zulu Lounde and Lady Bunny and Dimetri at Southern Funk, March 23, 1986 / May 1, 1986; ID: 357.0017; 243836 (Box 1, Media ID: 357.0017, Case 357.0017)
    This video documents the March 23, 1986 at The Zulu Lounge, including a performance by Shazork (Lady Bunny, DJ Dmitri Brill, and Sister Dimension's band). After the show, Nelson spends a little time backstage with the band. It also shows the May 1, 1986, Lady Bunny and Dimetri performance at Southern Funk Cafe.
  - Disney Show at Limelight, March 2, 1986; ID: 357.0018; 243837 (Box 1, Media ID: 357.0018, Case 357.0018)
  - Brant and Rhonda's Wedding, October 9, 1985; ID: 357.0019; 243838 (Box 1, Media ID: 357.0019, Case 357.0019)
    On October 9, 1985, Nelson films Brant and Rhonda's wedding ceremony and party.
  - Michael Musto and the Must in Boston, undated; ID: 357.0020; 243846 (Box 1, Media ID: 357.0020, Case 357.0020)
    This undated video starts with Nelson spending time with friends. The group then loads up a van and drives to Boston for a concert by Michael Musto and the Must. The video shows the band warming up and then spending time in their hotel.
  - The Patricia Field Store, January 29, 1986; ID: 357.0021; 243847 (Box 1, Media ID: 357.0021, Case 357.0021)
    On January 29, 1986, Nelson creates a video for Pat Field in the Patricia Field Store, which is having a sale.
  - Bobby's Birthday Party, undated; ID: 357.0022; 243848 (Box 1, Media ID: 357.0022, Case 357.0022)
    Nelson and friends attend a birthday party for Bobby Reed in an apartment in this undated video.
  - The Now Explosion at the Pyramid Club, December 26, 1985; ID: 357.0023; 243850 (Box 1, Media ID: 357.0023, Case 357.0023_pt.1, Case 357.0023_pt.2)
    Disc one shows The Now Explosion performing at The Pyramid Club. Towards the end of their performance, they're joined on stage by RuPaul. After the show, Nelson goes backstage to spend time with the band.
    Disc two is a continuation of The Now Explosion's performance at The Pyramid Club on the same night. After a short break, they take the stage again, and RuPaul once again joins them for a few songs. Lady Bunny also joins them onstage for a couple songs.
  - Now Explosion - Pyramid, November 9, 1984; ID: 357.0602; 277173 (Box 1, Media ID: 357.0602)
    Curently unavailable.
  - Buster Poindexter at Limelight, November 19, 1985; ID: 357.0024; 243851 (Box 1, Media ID: 357.0024, Case 357.0024)
    Nelson is backstage with Buster Poindexter and the other musicians while they warm up before their show at Limelight on November 19, 1985, then heads out to the audience. The show is celebrating Buster Poindexter's birthday. Susan Kirschner joins Buster on stage for several songs. Afterwards, Nelson goes backstage again briefly.
  - Cocktail Girlz in Atlanta 688, March 1, 1986; ID: 357.0025; 243852 (Box 1, Media ID: 357.0025)
    Currently unavailable until duplication occurs.
  - Provincetown, Massachusetts Part 2, August 1984; ID: 357.0026; 243853 (Box 1, Media ID: 357.0026, Case 357.0026)
    End of DVD is damaged.
    On August 29 and 30, 1984, Nelson records his stay in Provincetown. Nelson and Sylvia Miles explore Provincetown together, bumping into friends wherever they go.
  - Provincetown, Massachusetts Part 1, August 1984; ID: 357.0027; 243854 (Box 1, Media ID: 357.0027, Case 357.0027)
    On August 27 and 28, 1984, Nelson records his stay in Provincetown. The video features Nelson, Sylvia Miles, Bob Haas, and others exploring the town at a leisurely pace.
  - Michael Musto's Birthday #1, December 18, 1985; ID: 357.0028; 243855 (Box 1, Media ID: 357.0028, Case 357.0028_pt.1, Case 357.0028_pt.2)
    On disc one, Nelson and Sylvia Miles attend Michael Musto's birthday party at Amsterdam's restaurant with many others on December 18, 1985. The video ends with a group going outside to hail a cab.
    On disc two, more people arrive at the party, including a singing stripper, Jon St. John, and Andy Warhol. Nelson and friends leave the party and take a cab.
  - Michael Musto's Birthday #2, December 18, 1985; ID: 357.0035; 243862 (Box 2, Media ID: 357.0035, Case 357.0035)
  - Beyond the Valley of La Cage at Limelight, December 17, 1985; ID: 357.0029; 243856 (Box 1, Media ID: 357.0029, Case 357.0029)
    This video documents the December 17, 1985 drag show at Limelight, Beyond the Valley of La Cage. Nelson goes backstage and shows some of the performers getting ready for the night. Then he films the performance, which features drag queens impersonating their favorite pop stars. After the show, Nelson goes backstage to spend time with the performers.
  - Shazork at Pyramid, May 12, 1986; ID: 357.0030; 243857 (Box 1, Media ID: 357.0030, Case 357.0030)
    Nelson is backstage at the Pyramid Club with Shazork as they get ready to perform on May 12, 1986. He then films their short teaser performance, before filming their later full performance.
  - David Chicklet's Birthday Party, Shazork at Danceteria, and Shazork at the Pyramid Club, December 1985; ID: 357.0031; 243858 (Box 2, Media ID: 357.0031, Case 357.0031)
    This video opens with David Chicklet's tenth birthday party at Limelight on December 6, 1985, where Michael Musto and others make an appearance. After that, Nelson heads to Danceteria for Shazork's performance. The video also shows footage from December 15 at the Pyramid Club, for a show by an unidentified band, then Shazork at The Whispers Party at the Pyramid Club.
  - Joy Askew at Cat Club, January 14, 1986; ID: 357.0032; 243859 (Box 2, Media ID: 357.0032, Case 357.0032)
    Nelson attends Joy Askew's performance at the Cat Club on January 14, 1986. He heads backstage briefly before Askew's set, then records the entire show. Before the video ends, he parties backstage for a bit.
  - New Year's Eve at Pyramid with Love Delegation and Shazork #2, December 31, 1986; ID: 357.0033; 243860 (Box 2, Media ID: 357.0033, Case 357.0033_pt.1, Case 357.0033_pt.2)
    On disc one, Nelson is backstage at the Pyramid Club with friends as they wait for the performances on New Year's Eve. Nelson then heads to the dancefloor for a set by Peter Zaremba's Love Delegation with Wendy Wild and Liz Luv from Das Frlines.
    On disc two, Peter Zaremba's Love Delegation's performance continues. After the set, Nelson once again goes backstage. Throughout the video, a drag queen naps on a couch while everyone parties around her, but Nelson keeps returning to her. Shazork takes the stage and performs. The video ends with Nelson and the band backstage.
  - The Saint: Fashions for Japan, January 16, 1986; ID: 357.0034; 243861 (Box 2, Media ID: 357.0034, Case 357.0034)
  - Fire Island, July 4, 1976; ID: 357.0036; 243863 (Box 2, Media ID: 357.0036, Case 357.0036)
  - New Year's Eve at Pyramid with Michael London and 3 TEENS KILL 4, December 31, 1986; ID: 357.0037; 243864 (Box 2, Media ID: 357.0037, Case 357.0037)
  - 5 Ninth Ave Backyard (with Bob, Albert, Gaga, Maison, Johnny and the Pets), undated; ID: 357.0038; 243865 (Box 2, Media ID: 357.0038, Case 357.0038)
  - 5 Ninth Avenue (with Douglas and tour of apartment), undated; ID: 357.0039; 243866 (Box 2, Media ID: 357.0039, Case 357.0039)
  - Gabriel Rotello's Eclectic Circus at Limelight, March 10, 1986; ID: 357.0040; 243867 (Box 2, Media ID: 357.0040, Case 357.0040_pt.1, Case 357.0040_pt.2)
  - Downtown Divas I at Limelight, April 9, 1985; ID: 357.0041; 243868 (Box 2, Media ID: 357.0041, Case 357.0041)
  - Shazork at Pyramid, Phoebe Legere at Limelight, February 9, 1986; ID: 357.0042; 243869 (Box 2, Media ID: 357.0042, Case 357.0042)
  - Pop Tarts at Danceteria, December 15, 1986; ID: 357.0043; 243870 (Box 2, Media ID: 357.0043, Case 357.0043)
  - The Sound of Muzak, April 21, 1986; ID: 357.0044; 243871 (Box 2, Media ID: 357.0044, Case 357.0044_pt.1, Case 357.0044_pt.2)
  - Sylvia Miles Screen Test, Brant's Music Video, undated; ID: 357.0045; 243872 (Box 2, Media ID: 357.0045, Case 357.0045)
  - Dinah Prince at Limelight, June 2, 1986; ID: 357.0046; 243873 (Box 2, Media ID: 357.0046, Case 357.0046)
  - Gaylord, Alexis, John Sex, Joey Arias at Limelight, February 2, 1986; ID: 357.0047; 243874 (Box 2, Media ID: 357.0047, Case 357.0047)
  - Cookie Watkins and Company at Cat Club, February 18, 1986; ID: 357.0048; 243875 (Box 2, Media ID: 357.0048, Case 357.0048)
  - Ethyl Eichelberger in Leer and Casanova at Performing Garage, March 8, 1986; ID: 357.0049; 243876 (Box 2, Media ID: 357.0049, Case 357.0049_pt.1, Case 357.0049_pt.2)
  - Follies at Cat Club, Walking Blackout (late night), Pyramid, March 13, 1986; ID: 357.0050; 243877 (Box 2, Media ID: 357.0050, Case 357.0050)